Guide to the Max Kreutzberger Palestine Collection AD.MC.009
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Max Kreutzberger Palestine collection
1917-1948
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.009
3.75 Linear Feet in 9 document boxes.
The Max Kreutzberger Palestine Collection contains official reports, debates, correspondence and opinion literature regarding the administration of Palestine, collected by Max Kreutzberger, a German Jewish historian and social worker.
Conditions Governing Access:
The collection is open to researchers. For more information contact nyuad-asc-group@nyu.edu.
Arrangement:
The order was defined by the bookseller's collection guide, which categorizes the collection into 11 series based on origin. Series are often related to a single committee or organization, except in the case of the final 'miscellaneous' category. Within each series, the documents are arranged chronologically.
Source: Adapted from bookseller's collection guide: 'The Palestine Problem: An Important Collection of Documents on Zionism and the Administration of Palestine, 1920-1948', Walkabout Books.
Biographical / Historical
This collection was assembled by Max Kreutzberger, a prominent German Jewish historian and social worker. He was born in Germany in 1900, but spent much of the 1930s in Palestine before eventually moving to New York in 1955. Kreutzberger is perhaps best known for becoming the first director of the Leo Baeck Institute, a research library for German Jewish history in New York. During his lifetime, he amassed a collection of over 10,000 pages on Palestine. Kreutzberger died in 1978.
Source: Ritchey Oummia, Dianne, and Leo Baeck Institute Staff. "Guide to the Papers of Max Kreutzberger (1900-1978), 1848-1998 AR 7183 / MF 798." Leo Baeck Institute. N.p., n.d. Web. 18 Nov. 2015
Provenance:
NYUAD Library acquired the collection in August 2015 from Walkabout Books, who acquired it from the estate of Daniel Crosswell, Max Kreutzberger's son and original inheritor of the collection.
Related Materials
A larger group of the papers of Max Kreutzberger is held by the Leo Baeck Institute, New York. A finding aid for that collection, as well as a digitized copy of its contents, can be found on the website of the Institute, at: https://digifindingaids.cjh.org/?pID=121525.
Scope and Contents:
The Max Kreutzberger Palestine Collection contains offical and unofficial documents relating to Palestine in the period 1915-1948 (largely 1920-1948). It contains official materials, including transcripts of speeches, relating to the organizations responsible for deciding the future of Palestine, such as the UN Special Commission on Palestine (UNSCOP), the British Government and the Anglo-American Committe of Inquiry. The Kreutzberger Collection also includes records of the British administration of Palestine in the form of administrative reports and command papers ('white papers'). Unofficial documents include correspondence, newspaper editorials and extensive opinion literature on Palestine. Finally, the collection contains multiple publications from Zionist organisations of the time.
Source: Adapted from bookseller's collection guide: 'The Palestine Problem: An Important Collection of Documents on Zionism and the Administration of Palestine, 1920-1948', Walkabout Books.
Zionist Congress; Religious Sites; Mandates -- Great Britain; League of Nations; Jerusalem; House of Commons (Great Britian); Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry, 1945-1946; Zionism -- Palestine -- History; Palestine Commission on the Disturbances of August 1929 (Great Britain); Palestine; United Nations Palestine Commission; British -- Palestine -- History; Colonialism -- History -- Middle East; Arab Higher Committee; Israel; Jewish Agency for Palestine; League for Jewish-Arab Rapprochement and Cooperation; Palestinian Communist Party; Agudath, Israel; Maps; United Nations; Western Wall; House of Lords (Great Britain)
- Series I: Command Papers
  - Correspondence with the Palestine Arab Delegation and the Zionist Organization., June 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mandate for Palestine 1992. Letter from the Secretary of the Cabinet to the Secretary-General of the League of Nations on July 1, 1922, enclosing a note in reply to Cardinal Gasparri's letter of May, 15 1922, addressed to the Secretary-General of the League of Nations., July 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between His Majesty's Governmentand the French Government respecting the Boundary line between Syria and Palestine from the Mediterranean to El Hamme (with three maps)., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Western or Wailing Wall in Jerusalem: Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Palestine. Statement of Policy by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom., October 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Proposed New Constitution for Palestine., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence between Sir Henry McMahon His Majesty's High Commissioner at Cairo and the Sherif Hussein of Mecca July 1915- March 1916 (with a Map)., 1915-16, 1939; 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Report of a Committee set up to consider certain correspondence between Sir Henry McMahon (his Majesty's High Commissioner in Egypt) and the Sharif of Mecca in 1915 and 1916., 1915-16, 1939; 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statements Made on Behalf of His Majest's Government during the Year 1918 in Regard to the Future Status of Certain Parts of the Ottoman Empire., 1918, 1939; 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Palestine. Statement of Policy Presented by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to Parliament by Command of His Majesty., May 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Palestine. Statement of Information Relating to Acts of Violence., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Proposals for the Future of Palestine. July 1946-February 1947., 1946-7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Progress Report of the United Nations Mediator on Palestine. Rhodes 16th Spetember, 1948. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Shaw Commission
  - Report of the Commission on the Palestine Disturbances of August, 1929., March 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Palestine. Statement with Regard to British Policy., May 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Report of the Commission appointed by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, with the Approval of the League of Nations, to determine the rights and Claims of Moslems and Jes in connection with the Western or Wailing Wall at Jerusalem, December 1930., December 1930, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Report of the Palestine Enquiry Commission (Commission on the Palestine Disturbances of August 1929). Examination and Criticism. Vital Omissions and Misstatements., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Palestine Royal Commission
  - Subseries A: Official Documents
    - Palestine Royal Commission Report, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Palestine Royal Commission. Memoranda Prepared by the Government of Palestine., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Palestine Royal Commission. Minutes of Evidence Heard at Public Sessions (with Index)., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Palestine. Statement of Policy by His Majesty's Government in the United Kindom., July 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Policy in Palestine, Despatch Dated 23rd December 1937, from the Secretary of State for the Colonies tothe High Commissioner for Palestine., January 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Palestine Partition Commission Report., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Unofficial Documents
    - Memorandum Submitted to the Palestine Royal Commission on Behalf of the Jewish Agengy for Palestine., November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Memorandum Submitted to the Palestine Royal Commission on Behalf of the Jewish Agency for Palstine, Appendices., November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Jewish Health System and Government Policy, Reprinted from Memorandum Submitted to the Palestine Royal Commission on Behalf of Vaad Leumi, The general Council of the Jewish Community of Palestine., December 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Jewish People and Palestine. Statement Made Before The Palestine Royal Commission in Jerusalem on November 25, 1936., November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Das judische Volk und Palastina. Erklarung vor der Koniglichen Palastina-Kommission in Jerusalem am 25. November 1936., November 1936, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Evidence Submitted to the Palestine Royal Commission, House of Lords, London, February 11th, 1937, on Behalf of the New Zionisr Organisation. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Partition of Palestine", July 10 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Peel Bericht und Judenstaat., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Observations on the Report of the Palestine Royal Commission., June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Partition of Palestine. Suggested Alterations in Proposed Frontiers., 1938 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Anglo-American Committee of Enquiry
  - Dates and Contents for the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry, 8-25 March 2015., 8-25 March 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A Survey of Palestine Prepared in December 1945 and January 1946 for the Information of the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Volume 1. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - A Survey of Palestine Prepared in December 1945 and January 1946 for the Information of the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Volume 2. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Anglo-American Committe of Enquiry regarding the problems of European Jewry and Palestine., April 1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Report to the United States Government, His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - We Warned You, Gentlemen. Testimony before the Anglo American Committee of Inquiry on Palestine., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Jewish Case Before the Anglo-American Committee on Palestine, as presented by the Jewish Agency for Palestine. Statements and Memoranda., 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Jerusalem (Palestine). 8 March 1946. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Jerusalem (Palestine). 12 March 1946. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee. Jerusalem (Palestine). 13 March 1946. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Jerusalem (Palestine). 14 March 1946. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Jerusalem (Palestine). 15 March 1946. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Public Hearings Before the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry. Jerusalem (Palestine). 25 March 1946. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series V: United Nations Special Committee on Palestine
  - The Arab Higher Commission, Its Origins, Personnel and Purposes. The Documentary Record Submitted to The United Nations, May 1947 by the Nation Associates. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report to the General Assembly by the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine, Geneva Switzerland, 31st August, 1947. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annexes, Appendices and Maps to the Report by the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine, Geneva, Switzerland, 31st August, 1947. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - United Nations Special Committee on Palestine 1947, Summary of Recommendations. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Palestine- Divided or United? The Case for a Bi-National Palestine Before the United Nations., 1947 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Politcal History of Palestine Under British Administration., July 1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Supplementary Memorandum by the Government of Palestine, including Notes on Evidence given to the United Nations Special Committee in Palestine up to the 12th July 1947. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Reply to the Government of Palestine's Memorandum on the Administration of Palestine Under the Mandate, Submitted to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., August 1947 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Zionism and the Arab World. Memorandum Submitted to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., 1947 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The Jewish Plan for Palestine. Memoranda and Statements presented by the Jewish Agency for Palestine to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Supplement to the Survey of Palestine. Notes Compiled for the information of the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., June 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rabbi Fishman's Address to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Summary of Statement by Dr. Chaim Weizmann before the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Statement made by the Chief Rabbi Dr. I. Herzog to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Address delivered to UNSCOP by Samuel Mikunis, Secretary of the Communist Party of Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Plan for the Independence of Palestine. Address by Meir Vilner, Secretary of the Communist Party of Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Palestine- A Police State. Address by Dr. W. Erlich, member of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Palestine., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Statement by Aharon Cohen, Secretary of the League for Jewish-Arab Rapprochment and Co-Operation., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Oral Evidence given by Mr. E. Preminger, Member of the Central Committee of the Palestine Communist Union., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Statement by Rabbi I. M. Lewin, Chairman of Agudath Israel, To UNSCOP., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Translation of the Speech by Rabbi Selig Reuben Bengis, President Religious Law Courts., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Statement by Rabbi M. Glikman-Porush to UNSCOP., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Testimony of Mr. F. Bernstein before UNSCOP., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Evidence of Mr. Eliezer Kaplan before UNSCOP., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - The Jewish Agency for Palestine. Memorandum on Reconversion in Palestine., June 1947 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Memorandum to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine submitted by the League for Jewish-Arab Rapprochement and Co-operation., Undated. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Special Committee on Palestine, Verbatim Record of the Thirty-third Meeting (Public)., July 1947 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Administrative Reports
  - Report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1926., 1927 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Report by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1927., 1928 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Report by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1933., 1934 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Report by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1935., 1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Report by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1936., 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Report by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1937., 1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Report by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland to the Council of the League of Nations on the Administration of Palestine and Trans-Jordan for the Year 1938., 1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Parliamentary Debates
  - Official Report, Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons. Volume 313. No. 106. Friday, 19th June, 1936. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Lords, Official Report (Unrevised). Vol. 106. No. 94. Tuesday, 20th July, 1937. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Lords, Official Report (Unrevised). Vol. 106. No. 95. Tuesday, 20th July, 1937. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, Official Report. Volume 326. No. 149. Wednesday, 21st July, 1937. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons Official Report. Volume 326. No. 150. Wednesday, 21t=st July, 1937. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons Official Report. Volume 332. No. 69. Tuesday, 8th March, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons Official Report. Volume 341. No. 13. Thursday, 24th November, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Lords, Official Report (Unrevised). Vol. 111. No. 13. Thursday, 8th December, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, Official Report. Volume 347. No. 107. Monday, 22nd May, 1939. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, Official Report. Volume 347. No. 108. Tuesday, 23rd May, 1939. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, Official Report. Volume 350. No. 145. Monday, 20th July, 1939. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Parliamentary Debates (Hansard), House of Commons, Official Report. Volume 415. No. 37. Tuesday, 13th Nov., 1945., November 1945 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Other Government Documents
  - Palestine. Termination of the Mandate, 15th May, 1948. Statement prepared for public information by the Colonial Office and Foreign Office. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Series IX: Publications of the Jewish Agency for Palestine
  - Palastinadebatte im Englischen Unterhaus. Stenographischer Bericht uber die Verhandlungen im englischen Unterhaus vom 17. November 1930. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Report of the Executive of the Jewish Agency for Palestine submitted to the Fourth Meeting of the Council at Lucerne, September 4th-5th, 1935., September 1935 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Bericht der Exekutive der Jewish Agency for Palestine an die IV. Tagung des Council der Agency Lurzen, 1. Bis 5. September 1935. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Great Britain and Palestine 1915-1936., 1915-36, 1937; 1937 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Finanz-Bericht uber die Judenalijah aus Deutschland nach Palastina., August 1937 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Jewish Immigration into Palestine from Germany During 1933-1936., 1933-6, 1937; 1937 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Documents Relating to the McMahon Letters [with Map]., March 1939 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Promises and Afterthoughts. Notes of Certain White Papers Relating to the Palestine Conferences., May 1939 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Documents Relating to the Balfour Declaration and the Palestine Mandate., May 1939 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Documents and Correspondence Relating to Palestine., August 1939-March 1940 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The Balfour Declaration, Origins and Background., March 1940 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - National Income and Outlay in Palestine 1936., 1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Reply to Bevin, Analysis of the Foreign Secretary's Statements on Palestine., February 1946 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Documents Relating to the Palestine Problem., 1945 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series X: Publications Relating to the Zionist Congress
  - Report to the XIXth Zionist Congress and to the IVth Council of the Jewish Agency in Lucerne., July 1935 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Bericht an den XIX. Zionistenkongress und an den Council der Jewish Agency for Palestine in Lurzen., July 1935 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bericht an den XX. Zionistenkongress und an den Council der Jewish Agency for Palestine in Zurich., August 1937 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Report of the Executives of the Zionist Organisation and of the Jewish Agency for Palestine submitted to the XXth Zionist Congress and the Vth Session of the Council of the Jewish Agency at Zurich, August 1937. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Palestine 1937, British Public Opinion., Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Financial Report of the Executive of the Jewish Agency for the Years 5697, 5698, and the First half of 5699. (October 1936-March 1939). Submitted to the XXI Zionist Congress and the VI Session of the Council of the Jewish Agency at Geneva. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series XI: Miscellaneous
  - Britische Politik in Palastina. Rede des Kolonialministers Winston Churchill im englischen Unterhause am 4 Juli 1922., July 1922 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Palestine: The Fight for Jewish Freedom and Honour. Together with an Address by Mrs. Wedgwood., 1926 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Beitrage zur Frage unserer Propaganda:Ein Briefwechsel zwischen Herrn R.A. Max Jacobsohn und Herrn Kurt Blumenfeld nebst Aeusserungen fuhrender deutscher Zionisten., Undated, c.1928 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Juden und Araber in Palastina, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Juden und Araber in Mandat, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "The Palestine Question", October 1937 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Palestine and the British Empire, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Jewish Army, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Jews Arabs and the Middle East, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - The Progress of Zionism, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Palestine 1917-1944. Pamphlet No. 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Jewish National Home in Palestine: hearing Submitted to the Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives., February 1944 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The Jewish National Home in Palestine: Supplemental Statements to Hearing Submitted to the Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives., 1944 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Palestine and America's Role in the Middle East., July 1945 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Let Jews and Arabs Meet., February 1945 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Palestine Controversy: A Symposium. Papers Prepared for the Fabian Colonia Bureau, with an Introduction by H.N. Brailsford., 1945 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Summary of a Report of the Economic Planning Commission of the Aliyah Hadashah, Proposals for Consolidation and Immigration in Palestine., 1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Zionism at the Cross Roads, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Towards Union in Palestine. Essays on Zionism and Jewish-Arab Cooperation., 1947 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - The Zionist Question in its Scientific Setting., 1948 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Is this the way? A call to Jews., 1948 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Palestine, The Stark Facts and the Way Out., Undated, c.1948 (Box 9, Folder 13)